Guide to the Foster Family Collection of Ambrose Bierce Materials M2146
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Foster family collection of Ambrose Bierce materials
1858-1986
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Elkhart County Historical Society
M2146
3.0 Linear Feet: 2 boxes, 1 half-box, 1 flat box
Content Description
The collection consists of correspondence (including one letter from Ambrose Bierce to a family member), photographs, maps, field notes, receipts, dispatches, telegrams, and printed material, chiefly relating to the Civil War career of Bierce as a surveyor as well as his extended family in Indiana, especially sister Almeda Sophia Bierce Pittenger (the original source of this collection), father Marcus Aurelius and brothers Albert and Addison Bierce.
Of particular note to Civil War historians are the series of maps produced by the Union army's Army of the Cumberland on the Chattanooga Campaign, reflecting the borders between Tennessee, Georgia, and Alabama. Of the paper and linen printed maps, some have annotations, and most credit Captain William Emery Merrill. A few note that they were created from information from "captured rebel engineers." There are also maps drawn by Bierce himself. Note that Stanford's Ambrose Bierce Papers also contain material concerning the Civil War, including the sketchbook Bierce kept while serving as a Union topographer with the staff of General Hazen.
D.W. "Jim" Strauss originally loaned this collection to the Elkhart County Historical Society in Bristol, Indiana on behalf of his late wife Betty Ann, who had inherited it from her mother Grace Juanita Bussing Foster, Almeda's daughter. After Strauss's death, their daughters Cindra Heston and Debra Van Dyke decided to donate the Bierce collection to Stanford.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
[identification of item], Foster family collection of Ambrose Bierce materials (M2146). Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives, Stanford University Libraries, Stanford, Calif.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cindra Heston and Debra Van Dyke, 2016. Accession MSS 2016-175.
Biographical / Historical
Ambrose Gwinett Bierce was born in Meigs County, Ohio on June 24, 1842, the tenth child of Marcus Aurelius and Laura Sherwood Bierce. Little is known of his childhood; he became a printer's apprentice in Kosciusko County, Indiana, before entering the Kentucky Military Institute in 1859. Shortly before the outbreak of the Civil War, Bierce was a laborer and waiter in Elkhart, Indiana. Bierce enlisted in the 9th Regiment of Indiana Volunteers following Lincoln's call for volunteers and served for nearly the duration. Bierce was one of the few war veteran writers to have such front-lines experience, surviving some the war's most bloody battles, including Shiloh, Missionary Ridge, and Chickamauga. Bierce progressed in rank from private to lieutenant and became the acting topographical engineer on Gen. W. B. Hazen's staff. At the battle of Kenesaw Mountain, Bierce sustained a near-fatal head wound from which it took months to recover. It is clear that his war experiences did much to inform his "Bitter Bierce" persona.
Following the war, Bierce became an aid to Treasury Department agents collecting abandoned Southern property. He joined Hazen's surveying expedition to the Far West in 1866 and stayed on in San Francisco working for the U.S. Mint. In San Francisco Bierce began to pursue his literary interests. In 1868, he succeeded his friend James T. Watkins as the editor of News-Letter. Bierce married Mary Ellen Day on Christmas Day, 1871, and eventually had three children, Day, Leigh, and Helen.
From 1872 to 1874, Bierce was in England writing for Tom Hood's Fun and James Mortimer's Figaro. He returned to San Francisco in September of 1875. He edited several magazines for the next years, including Argonaut and the Wasp; he also wrote his Prattle and The Dance of Death. Bierce became a columnist for the San Francisco Examiner in 1887 and continued to produce his own books and stories. He was sent in 1896 by the Examiner to Washington, D.C. to cover the Railroad Funding Bill controversy. He stayed on in Washington as a political reporter for many years, all the while publishing his own literary work.
In late 1913, Bierce took a trip through the Southwest into Mexico where he mysteriously disappeared. It is likely that he became involved with the Mexican Revolution, traveling south with Pancho Villa and his troops, and met his fate at the hands of Federal soldiers near Chihuahua City.
Related Materials
Stanford Special Collections also holds the Ambrose Bierce Papers (M0080) https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082973
Letters to or from Bierce are also contained in the papers of David Starr Jordan, George Sterling, Eugene T. Sawyer, and Stephen Mallory White.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Authors, American.; Bierce, Ambrose, 1842-1914?; Elkhart County Historical Society; Bierce family
- Series 1. Photographs
  - Photographs AB1 - AB4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    “Mrs. Ambrose Bierce, Aunt Molly” – San Francisco, CA; E. H. Bierce, age 84; unknown family; “Uncle Will and Aunt Ann Good” – Mercer, photographer, Middleport, Ohio.
  - Photographs AB5 - AB8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    From brown envelope marked “Bierce”: Unknown woman; unknown man; unknown woman; “M. A. Bierce.”
  - Photographs AB9 - AB14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    One from white envelope: “To my Mother Addison” – J. Humphrey, Kimarnock, photographer; “Harrie Bierce Jr.” – J. H. Clark, photographer, Indianapolis; “Grandpa Bierce” - H. C. Millice, photographer, Warsaw, IN; unknown woman (poss. Mrs. Ambrose Bierce) – Elite, photographer, San Francisco; unknown children (boy & girl) – G. D. Morse, photographer, San Francisco; “Grace Pittinger Davis Bussing” – Parrot, photographer, Warsaw, IN.
  - Photographs AB15 - AB17, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    In envelope to Miss Hettie Pittinger, R. R. West, Warsaw, Indiana: “Grandpa Bierce” – H. C. Milice & Bro, photographer, Warsaw, IN; “Yours Truly, Lulu Tinsworth” (Bierce added in pencil), Uncle Al’s daughter – Elite, photographer, San Francisco; “Andrew Bierce” – Goff, photographer, Elkhart, IN.
  - Photographs AB18 - AB21, 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Next four photos appear to be of the same gentleman: Unknown gentleman in chair – postcard to Miss Hettie Pittinger, Nove. 23, 3pm, 1914; unknown gentleman in chair – postcard not addressed or mailed; unknown gentleman with hat – postcard addressed to Miss Hettie Pittinger, Nov. 22, 1912; unknown gentleman in chair with hat – postcard not addressed.
  - Photographs AB22 - AB25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    “Yours Truly, A. S. Bierce” – Haussler, photographer, San Francisco; A S. Bierce in military uniform; “Carlton A. Bierce” – Oakland, CA; Dag type of unknown older woman (Grandmother Bierce?); “Grandmother Bierce” – H. C. Milice & Bro., photographic artists, Warsaw, IN.
  - Photographs AB26 - AB29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    “Mrs. Laran, Springfield, Ohio, A dear friend gone”; “Ida E. Reber” – T. H. Bulla, photographer, Elkhart, IN; unknown woman – DeVos, photographer, Elkhart, IN; unknown older woman – Young & Carl, photographers, Cincinnati, Ohio.
  - Photographs AB30, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Ink (?) drawing of unknown gentleman dated 1858.
  - Photographs AB31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    “Harrie Bierce, 70 years”
  - Photographs AB32 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    “Laura Bierce, My Grandmother” – penciled to accentuate details.
  - Photographs AB33 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Unknown older gentleman – penciled to accentuate details, newspaper glued to back.
  - Photographs AB34 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    “Ambrose Bierce” – Netterville Briggs, photographers, London (one duplicate) – Nahl Bros. & Dickman, San Francisco.
  - Photographs AB35 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    “Harrie Bierce, 70 years” (possibly unknown gentleman in postcard previously recorded)
  - Photographs AB36 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    “Harrie Bierce Jr.” – Nicholson, IN with envelope.
  - Etching of California Authors (Box 1, Folder 15)
    From photograph folder, etching includes Ambrose Bierce.
- Series 2. Books and notebooks
  - A. J. Bierce's billfold (empty) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Army Officer's Pocket Companion and Manual for Staff Officers in the Field, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Written by William P. Craighill, published in 1862 by D. Van Nostrand, New York. Some water damage and worn spine.
  - Ambrose Bierce's Field Book for Map Notes (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Ambrose Bierce's filed book for map notes - signed "Lieut. A. G. Bierce A. Topl. Engr. Staff of Gen. Hazen." Includes drawings for Demi-Lune Post Pulaski, TN planned and constructed by A. G. Bierce; Cleveland, Tenn.; and Dallas, GA - good condition
  - Ambrose Bierce's signed copy of Gillespie's Land Surveying (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Gillespie's Land Surveying - Treatise on Land Surveying by W. M. Gillespie, LL. D., Civ. Eng. published by D. Appleton & Co. of New York - signed "A. G. Bierce Top Eng"
- Series 3. Ambrose Bierce army records
  - Discharge papers, medical report, and equipment issuance, 1864-1869 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Ambrose Bierce Army discharge papers and envelope. Lt. A. G. Bierce medical report for discharge (head wound). Equipment issuance letter from Army.
- Series 4. Civil War maps
  - Sketch of the Environs of Murfreesboro, Tenn.by Capt. N. Michler (linen with pencil notations), September 1862 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Topographical Sketch of the Battle Field of Stone River - Surveyed by Maj. J.F. Weyss, under direcrtion of Capt. N. Michler (small linen) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Map of Chattanooga [Tennessee] & Vicinity, by Capt. Wm. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 08/12/1863 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Map of Cleveland [Tennessee], by Capt. Wm. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers (torn/damaged), 08/14/1863 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Map of McLamore's Cove [i.e. McLemore Cove, Georgia], by Capt. Wm. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 08/26/1863 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Map of Bridgeport and Trenton [Georgia-Alabama border], compiled under the direction of Capt. W. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 08/28/1863 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Map of Stevenson, Alabama, compiled from Information, under the direction of Capt. W. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 08/29/1863 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Map of Chattanooga [Tennessee] & Vicinity, compiled from the Latest Informations, under direction of Capt. W. E. Merrill, 09/08/1863 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Map of Bridgeport [Alabama] & Vicinity, surveyed under the direction of Capt. W.E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 03/26/1864 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Map of A Part of Murray County, Georgia, compiled under the direction of Capt. W. E. Merrill, U.S. Engineers, 04/23/1864 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Map of 1st District, Campbell County, Georgia, Compiled under direction of Capt. W.E. Merrill (linen), 05/23/1864 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Maps of Part of Cobb County, Georgia; [one by] by H.C. Wharton (negative maps], 06/08/1896; 06/26/1864 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Land Map of DeKalb County, Georgia, 07/11/1864 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Map of Atlanta [Georgia], 07/15/1864 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Map of Chicamauga River [aka Chickamauga River, Tennessee] (small hand-drawn map) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Map of Dalton [Georgia] & vicinity, Compiled under direction of Capt. W.E. Merrill (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Map of parts of Fulton, Fayette & Campbell Counties [Georgia], From Surveys, State Maps, and Information (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Five maps/battle plans by Ambrose Bierce (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes Reynolds, Hazen, TRain Depot, W. & A. RR, "Encampment"; Includes Manchester, Lynchburg Road, Shelbyville Road, Duck River; Bearings in Tennessee Valley; Manchester to Normandy 08/06/1863 (signed); Lynchburg Road from Manchester S.W. 08/11/1863 (signed)
- Series 5. Newspaper articles
  newspapers and clippings in the collection date from 1881 to 1986 and are chiefly about Bierce or his family, including reports detailing his death which came to light c1919-1920 and a few of his own SF Examiner articles, mostly fragmented.
  - Small Newspaper Clippings (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Large Newspaper Clippings (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poem scrapbook (Box 2, Folder 34)
    small notebook with poems cut from newspapers.
- Series 6. Letters, correspondence, and receipts
  - Engineer Orders and Circulars, 1863 - 1864 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    “Head Quarters 2d Brig. 3d Div. 4th Corps Official Business”; letter to A. G. Bierce from Wm. E. Merrill, Capt. U. S. Engineers, Chief Topl. Engr. “Head Quarter Topl. Engr. Office; Army of the Cumberland Official Business”; General Orders No. 124 Head-Quarters Dept. of the Cumberland, Murfreesboro, TN, May 31, 1863 – instructions to corps, division, and brigade topographers from newly appointed Capt. W. E. Merrill, engineer in charge of topographical dept. – includes scale from C. Goddard; Addition to General Orders No. 124 Topographical Engineer Office, Murfreesboro, TN, June 23, 1863, Capt. Wm. Merrill – circular to corps, division, and brigade topographers including instructions for recording features, signed and dated; Engineering Circular No. 3, Topographical Engineering Office, August 12th, 1863, Capt. Wm. Merrill – information maps, technique, and colorization; Engineering Circular No. 4, Top. Eng. Office, Sept. 9th, 1863 – regarding engineering property, Capt. Merrill; Engineering Circular No. 5, Top. Eng. Office, Sept. 9th, 1863 – instructions for mapping Cherokee Purchase, northern portion of Georgia – Capt. Merrill. Circular of General-Headquarters Topl. Engr. Office, Army of the Cumberland letterhead Chattanooga, March 3rd, 1864 – list of maps available from Wm. A. Margestantz, Capt. Supt. Topl. Engl. Office – Brig. Gen. Hayes – 2nts Brig. 3 Div. 4th C.; Circular No. 6, Headquarters Topl. Engr. Office, Army of the Cumberland letterhead, Chattanooga, March 3rd, 1864 – instructions for replacement of Topl. Engr. And care of equipment, notes, etc. Wm. A. Margestantz, Capt. Supt. Topl. Eng Office.
  - Pamphlet of Circulars and Orders, 01/10/1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Issued from Top. Engr. Office - Army of the Cumberland, Chattanooga, TN.
  - Dispatches and Express Receipts, 1863-1866 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    In envelope “Dispatches & Express Receipts”; American Telegraph Company to S. B. Eaton; Southwestern Telegraph Company; Adams Express Company from A. G. Bierce to S. B. Eaton; Southern Express Company from C. C. Marsh to Mrs. J. L. Watson; United States Express Company; U. S. Military Telegraph Office from Eaton to Bierce; American Telegraph Company to A. G. Bierce; Western Union Telegraph Company from Wazen to A. G. Bierce; American Telegraph Company from Luther Martin to S. B. Eaton.
  - Engineering Orders, 1863 - 1866 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Army issue invoice; letter from Jack at Montgomery Jan. 10th, 1866 to Bierce on cotton receipt; Topl. Engr. Office Chattanooga engineering orders; Top. Egr. Office, Engineer order; Death announcement of Capt. John Earhart Aug. 10, 1863; letter to the Treasury Dept (copy) received Feb. 18, 1865; sketch “monument.”
  - Poem - The Awakening (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - List of Railroad, Bridges, and Tunnels, 08/24/1863 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Germania Fire Insurance Co. Ad Blotter, 07/01/1863 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    A. L. Selig, agent, Lawrence, KS
  - Money Order Application (Box 2, Folder 8)
    U. S. Postmaster, No. 6001-domestic form.
  - Chicago Scale Co. Booklet (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Illustrated descriptions and prices of useful articles of prominent firms.
  - Letter from Ambrose Bierce to Almeda Pittenger, 12/07/1911 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter from Ambrose Bierce to his sister. Sent from the Army-Navy Club, Washington, D.C. to Pittinger in Warsaw, Indiana.
  - Ambrose Bierce London Address (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Genealogical Notes and Letters (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Bierce Genealogical Society form letter May 9th, 1921 to Mr. A. J. Bierce; letter to Mrs. Almeda Pittenger on same day; Birth dates – death dates of Augustus Bierce and Albert Sherwood Bierce; Deaths – Arthur Middleton Bierce, Adelia, Wayne Bierce, Aurelius Bierce; Deaths – Arthur Middleton Bierce, Adelia Wayne Bierce, Aurelia Jane Bierce, Aurelius Bierce, Marcus A. Bierce, Laura Sherwood Bierce; Marriages – Marcus Aurelius Bierce and Laura Sherwood; Dwight Warren Chappell and Abigail Bell Bierce, William Good and Ann Maria Bierce, Benjamin Franklin Guthrie and Amelia Bierce; Deaths – Addison Bierce, Amelia Bierce, Ann Maria Good, Augustus Bierce, Abigail Bell B. Chappell; Vitals on Marcus Aurelius Bierce, Laura Sherwood, Abigail Bell Bierce, Amelia Bierce, Ann Marie Bierce, Addison Bierce, Doretta Ferdinand.
  - Curtis Fenn Genealogical Research, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Letters to Almeda Pittenger re: descendants of Hezekiah Bierce; Curtis Fenn's mother was Harriet Almeda Bierce.
  - Marcus Aurelius Letter, 03/16/1869 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes word of Ambrose.
  - Marcus Aurelius Letter, 12/05/1869 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Regarding new home.
  - Abigail Bierce Letter, 04/20/1894 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Sent to Mrs. A. S. Pittenger re: general family activities.
  - Abigail Bierce Letter, 03/24/1911 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Sent to Mrs. A. S. Pittenger re: details of LIbbie's funeral.
  - Addison Bierce Letters, 1858 - 1913 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Attempts to re-establish connection with estranged family; Son Harry's loss of wife and son; Divorce from Doretta; Working in circus known as Add Bryron; More details of divorce Travels and illness; experiences and reflection in travels; Ambrose is mentioned in regards to visiting battlefields.
  - Albert Bierce Letters, 1876 - 1922 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Re: photo of Ambrose; envelope to Mrs. William Bussing; letter to Mrs. Almeda Pittenger re: Carl and Lora, Ambrose in Washington; to Mrs. Almeda Pittenger re: Leigh's death, Carlton's marriage in Alaska, Ambrose Bierce's address; memories of youth, Ambrose's asthma; Ambrose in Washington, interested in publishing house in NY and Washington; re: Ab's death; Ab's illness; father's death and Ambrose in San Francisco; death of Gus; trip to Glacier Pt. and memories of mother.
  - Ida Letters, 1910 - 1912 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    From Hotel Chapman, Los Angeles to mother - re: hotel, trip, illness; general info; from Redlands - includes price of groceries, letter to Nina Bussing, letter to mother and Grace re: trip to California; envelope postmarked March 21, 1912; letter to mother, Nela, and cousins from Portland, OR re: travels and family.
  - Old Cousins, Van Guilder, CCF, 1895 - 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    To Grace Bussing from Cora A. Van Gilder; to Almeda Pittenger from Columbus Fuller; to Grace Bussing from Cora A. Van Gilder; to Almeda Pittenger from C. C. Fuller; to Almeda Pittenger from C. Van Gilder; to A. S. Pittenger.
  - Letters to Almeda Pittenger, 1895 - 1911 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Group photo from Annie Mauck; two men in suits (man in wrinkled suit is Howard, the other is Will); Aunt Gracie; Aunt Meda; from Samuel and Hattie Cary.
  - E. Bierce Letters, 1912 - 1918 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Two letters on different dates addressed to Almeda Pittenger.
  - Ambrose Bierce and Charles Warren Stoddard (Box 2, Folder 24)
    "Ambrose Bierce and Charles Warren Stoddard: Some Unpublished Correspondence", reprint from The Huntington Library Quarterly, May Issue 1960, Vol. XXIII, No. #, pg. 261-292.
  - Mrs. Earl Foster Research (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Mrs. Earl Foster family records (poss. from Bierce family Bible), and assortedpages dealing with marriages, deaths, births - Ambrose's immediate family info.
  - Family Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Miscellaneous family correspondence and newspaper clippings belonging to Almeda Pittenger.
  - Letters of Inquiry (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Letters of inquiry for collection from various scholars.
  - Columbia University Correspondence, 03/14/1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Also includes Quarterly News Letter Spring 1961.
  - Betty Strauss, Time Life Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Requiem to Jane Elliot Boyd Davis (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pittenger Rent Receipt, 01/03/1909 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sir William Mulock's Philosophy of Life (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Assorted Correspondence and Papers (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Letter with envelope to Grace Bussing from John Merrill Davis from Rio Grande, Ohio; Christmas postcard to Almeda Pittenger from cousin Jane Chinworth; photograph of Carlton Bierce; postcard photograph of unknown older woman and man; photograph of Ambrose Bierce (?); letter with envelope to Grace Bussing from John Merrill Davis; photograph of "Uncle Ambrose Bierce" - Nahl Bros. & Dickman: Artists and Photographers, San Francisco; photograph of Albert Bierce - Morse's Gallery of the Cumberland, Nashville, TN; photograph of Addison Bierce - Edward J. Cobb photographer, San Francisco; blank papers and envelope; jacket of accounts book; Indiana State "Chautauqua" Assembly program 1893; Year Book of the Ladies' Society of the First Presbyterian Church signed by Juanita Bussing Foster.
- Series 7. Miscellaneous
  - Original collection inventory, museum exhibition card, article photocopies (Box 1, Folder 21)
    The collection inventory and plaque provided by Elkhart County Historical Museum. Newspaper articles regarding the museum's exhibit.
  - Card/announcement, Mollie E. Day and Mr. and Mrs. A. G. Bierce (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Possibly from the wedding of Mollie Day and Ambrose Bierce. Also icluded, two train tickets from the Lake Shore & Mich. Southern - Toledo to Chicago, South Bend to Goshen.
- Series 8. Drafting tools and desk
  - Wood field desk for drafting—green felt lining, compartment for drafting implements and other supplies
  - Field glass in black case
  - Theodolite telescope in brown leather case
  - Survey/drafting instruments in velvet-lined case: 5 assorted drawing compasses; 1 six inch wooden ruler
  - Compass for drafting (metal)
  - Protractor: 180 degrees (metal)